<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An exhortation to trust in God, and not to despair of His help and fall from Him, in this dark time of popery that is coming upon the church written by Digby Bull.</title>
            <author>Bull, Digby.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 107 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A30060</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B5411</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6962</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11625682</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11625682</idno>
            <idno type="VID">47917</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A30060)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 47917)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 484:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An exhortation to trust in God, and not to despair of His help and fall from Him, in this dark time of popery that is coming upon the church written by Digby Bull.</title>
                  <author>Bull, Digby.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 41 p. ;  20 cm. </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:47917:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:47917:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN EXHORTATION To TRUST in GOD, And not to Deſpair of his HELP <hi>And fall from Him, in this dark Time of</hi> Popery <hi>that is coming upon the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Written by <hi>Digby Bull</hi> M.A. and late Rector of <hi>Sheldon</hi> in <hi>Warwick-ſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the Author; and are to be Sold by <hi>John Whitlock</hi> near <hi>Stationers-Hall.</hi> 1695.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:47917:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:47917:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Iſaiah XXVI.IV.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Trust ye in the Lord for ever: For in the Lord <hi>JEHOVAH</hi> is everlaſting ſtrength.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>SUCH is the uncertainty and inſtability of this reſtleſs world at all times, that we can place no Truſt and Confidence therein, nor in any of our Poſſeſſions and Enjoyments here below, having but an uncertain Tenure of them at the beſt, and may be ſoon diſpoſſeſt and turned out of them. And ſo wave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and unconſtant is our Condition here, that we muſt confeſs with the Patriarchs of old, that we are like ſtrangers and pilgrims and wanderers here upon the earth, and have no fixed and ſure Abiding here, or any Rock wherein we may ſecurely repoſe our Hopes and Confidence. Nor does it ſeem to be the will of God that we ſhould be placed in ſuch a ſure and ſecure condition here, leſt we ſhould be like the <hi>Jews,</hi> of whom it is ſaid in that Song of <hi>Moſes,</hi> Deut. 32.18; <hi>Of the Rock that begat thee thou art un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mindful, and haſt forgotten God that formed thee:</hi> And too great a ſecurity here will be apt to make us like them, and to do ſo too. For the greater exerciſe of our Faith and Truſt-in Almighty God do we ſeem to be placed here in a more unſetled and mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table condition, wherein we are like ſome times to be expoſed to great Straits and Dangers and Neceſſities and Wants; and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we ſhall ſtand in great need of the Divine Help and Aſſiſtance of Almighty God; and are in an eſpecial manner then to call upon him for it, and to truſt in and rely upon him; and ſhall then be ſure to find him ready to ſuccor and help us, ſo far as he ſees it to be convenient for us, and ſo far as ſhall be ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient for us. And through the great wickedneſs and corruption
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:47917:3"/> of Mankind and the ſinful Children of this World, is our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition here like to be the worſe, and we muſt expect ſome times to be expoſed to great diſtreſs and hazards, and to have our very Lives perhaps too to lie at the Stake, and ſhall here find no help nor ſuccour to deliver us from our Fears and Dangers, but muſt have recourſe to Almighty God alone for help and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance from all our Diſtreſſes and Hazards whatſoever. And now have we cauſe to expect great Trouble and Perplexity, and that we muſt undergo the peril of loſing our very Lives; and ſhall have more than ordinary cauſe to fly to Almighty God for Refuge and Help and Protection: For I am confident that the time is now nigh at hand wherein Popery will prevail over the Proteſtant Church for a time; and we muſt expect very ſharp threatnings from the Papiſts when they have once gotten the upper hand. And therefore have I made choice of theſe words of the Prophet for the Subject of my preſent diſcourſe, wherein all the true Servants of God are exhorted to put their Truſt and Confidence in Almighty God at all times; and are aſſured that they ſhall find him a never-failing Refuge to all ſuch as have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to him and rely upon him. <hi>Trust ye in the Lord for ever: For in the Lord Jehovah is everlaſting ſtrength.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In theſe words then we have theſe two parts;</p>
            <p n="1">I. An Exhortation or Command to truſt in the Lord at all times. <hi>Truſt ye in the Lord for ever.</hi> And</p>
            <p n="2">II. The reaſon wherewith this Exhortation and Precept is backed, and why we ſhould do ſo; and that is becauſe of his ſure and certain Help and Aſſiſtance at all times: <hi>For in the Lord Jehovah is everlaſting ſtrength,</hi> or <hi>the Rock of Ages,</hi> as it is in the margent, and in the Hebrew.</p>
            <p n="1">I. An Exhortation and Command to truſt in the Lord at all times.</p>
            <p>God requires this of us, both as a Duty towards him, that we ſhould firmly rely upon his word and prom ſes, and place our whole Truſt in him at all times; And alſo for our own ſupport and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, and to chear our heavy hearts in all times of Diſtreſs, (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſuch as this which is now coming upon us;) That we ſhould then reſt and depend upon him for his divine Help and Aſſiſtance,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:47917:3"/> and ſecurely place our Confidence in him, with full aſſurance that he will not then forſake and fail us. And</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> We are hereby taught to put our Truſt and Confidence in no other, and to rely upon and confide in nothing elſe. In be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing commanded to truſt in the Lord <hi>Jehovah,</hi> we are tacitly here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by forbidden to truſt in any other God, or to place our truſt and confidence in any thing elſe beſides him. And this is the firſt Commandment of the Decalogue, that we ſhould have no other Gods before him. But in placing our chief truſt in any thing elſe, we perform an high act of religious duty thereto, and give God's honour and due to another, and do hereby in a great meaſure make it a God. And we may ſee that we are forbidden by poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive commands to truſt in any thing elſe beſides Almighty God, and that a Wo and Curſe is pronounced againſt ſuch, and that they are like to find no good in ſo doing.</p>
            <p>We are forbidden to truſt in Riches, and to place our Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in our worldly wealth and earthly treaſures. <hi>Charge them that are rich in this world</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy,</hi> 1 Tim. 6.17.) <hi>that they be not high-minded, nor truſt in uncertain riches; but in the living God.</hi> This is but vain confidence to place any truſt in them, as the Apoſtle here ſheweth. And ſaith <hi>Solomon,</hi> Pro. 23.5; <hi>Wilt thou ſet thine eyes upon that which is not? For riches certainly make themſelves wings; they fly away as an eagle towards heaven.</hi> It is great folly, as well as ſin, to rely upon them: For, as he ſaith Prov. 11.28, <hi>He that truſteth in his riches, ſhall fall.</hi> And in no ſtead in the needful time of trouble will they ſtand him in, that relies upon them, as <hi>Solomon</hi> alſo ſheweth. Prov. 11.4. <hi>Riches profit not in the day of wrath.</hi> When there is the moſt need af all, theſe will then ſignify nothing to a man's ſafety and ſecurity. And in this dark time which is coming upon us, I conceive, that they will rather add to the ſorrow and miſery, than to the comfort and ſafety of ſuch as are the great Maſters of them. And to diſſuade us the more from truſting in them, and to ſhew us the great miſchief in ſo doing, we may take notice of what our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Lord hath ſaid, viz, That ſuch as do ſo ſhall very hardly enter into the Kingdom of Heaven, and are in great danger of periſhing eternally. Mar. 10.23. <hi>And Jeſus looked round about, and ſaith unto his diſciples; How hardly ſhall they that have riches enter into
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:47917:4"/> the Kingdom of God! And the diſciples were aſtoniſhed at his words. But Jeſus anſwereth again, and ſaith unto them; children, how hard is it for them that truſt in riches, to enter into the Kingdom of God! It is eaſier for a camel to go thorow the eye of a needle, than for a rich man to enter into the Kingdom of God.</hi> By truſting in theſe, men are like to block up the path of Life againſt themſelves. We are ſtrictly forbid, we ſee, to truſt in riches, or in any worldly wealth and earthly treaſure.</p>
            <p>And we are alſo forbid to truſt in an Arm of Fleſh, or to rely upon any humane Power. We are not to place our Truſt and Confidence in any Kings and Princes and great Men of the earth; nor in any Armies and Naval Forces and Warlike Preparations. The doing of this is ſinful and evil, and theſe will prove but weak and helpleſs Deities to ſuch as rely upon them. Pſal. 146.3—, ſaith the Pſalmiſt there; <hi>Put not your truſt in princes, nor in the the ſon of man, in whom there is no help. His breath goeth forth, he returneth to his earth, in that very day his thoughts periſh.</hi> Theſe are of a mortal and periſhing nature themſelves, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not preſerve themſelves; and much leſs then are they able to help and ſave others that rely upon them. And a wo is denounced againſt ſuch as truſt in the help of man. Iſ. 30.1—. <hi>Wo to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious children, ſaith the Lord, that take counſel, but not of me, and that cover with a covering, but not of my Spirit, that they may add ſin to ſin. That walk to go down into Egypt (and have not aſked at my mouth) to ſtrengthen themſelves in the ſtrength of Pharaoh, and to truſt in the ſhadow of Egypt.</hi> And we may ſee in the verſes fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing what help and comfort they were like to find in ſo doing, ver. 3. <hi>Therefore ſhall the ſtrength of Pharaoh be your ſhame</hi> (ſaith God by the Prophet) <hi>and the truſt in the ſhadow of Egypt your confuſion.</hi> And ver. 5; <hi>They were all aſhamed of a people that could not profit them, nor be an help, nor profit; but a ſhame and alſo a reproach.</hi> Here we ſee how we are like to ſpeed, if we truſt in an Arm of Fleſh, and place our confidence in humane Power; we muſt then expect nothing but ſhame and reproach and confuſion. And to this purpoſe, Iſ. 31.1: <hi>Wo to them that go down to Egypt for help, and ſtay on horſes, and truſt in chariots, becauſe they are many; and in horſemen, becauſe they are very ſtrong: But they look not unto the holy One of Iſrael, neither ſeek the Lord.</hi> And what the iſſue
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:47917:4"/> of ſuch truſt and confidence is like to be, we may alſo ſee here, ver. 3; <hi>Now the Egyptians are men, and not God; and their horſes fleſh, and not ſpirit: when the Lord ſhall ſtretch out his hand, both he that helpeth ſhall fall, and he that it holpen ſhall fall down, and they ſhall fail together.</hi> Such diſappointment muſt men expect from their vain confidence in all humane Force and Power. And ſuch as truſt in an Arm of Fleſh are curſed, as God declareth by the Prophet Jeremiah, 17.5—; <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, curſed be the man that truſteth in man, and maketh Fleſh his Arm, and whoſe heart departeth from the Lord. For he ſhall be like the heath in the deſert, and ſhall not ſee when good cometh, but ſhall inhabit the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched places in the wilderneſs, in a ſalt land, and not inhabited.</hi> Such as forſake God, and truſt not in his Help, but place their hopes and confidence in humane Power, muſt expect no good, but ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and miſery to attend them in ſo doing.</p>
            <p>Nor are we to place our confidence in our wit and knowledg and ſtrength of body &amp;c, and to idolize them, as the Prophet ſheweth. Ier. 9.23— <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, Let not the wiſe man glory in his wiſdom; neither let the mighty man glory in his might; let not the rich man glory in his riches: But let him that glorieth, glory in this, that he underſtandeth and knoweth me, that I am the Lord</hi>—. We are not to truſt in theſe, nor in any other Idol that we may make to our ſelves; but in the Lord <hi>Jehovah</hi> the living and true God. For to truſt in any thing elſe ſhews diſreſpect and infidelity towards him, and is a derogation from his infinite Power and Goodneſs, and is ſinful and evil; and in ſo doing we ſhall be miſerably deluded, and may expect to have our hopes and confidence fruſtrated and diſappointed. And ſuch as ſhall now, in this dark Time which is coming upon us, betake them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to Arms on the one hand; or fall to Popery on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hand, to ſecure themſelves; I fear that ſuch will be in great danger of periſhing, and loſing their Lives. But I hope that all thoſe that put their truſt in Almighty God, and with faith and patience wait for his bleſſed Help and Protection, will be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved alive, notwithſtanding their hazard and danger is like to be very great. And the more to prevail with us to do ſo,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> We may ſee that we are often exhorted and enjoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the ſacred Scriptures to put our Truſt and Confidence
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:47917:5"/> in Almighty God at all times, and upon all accounts, eſpecially when we have the moſt need of Relief and Protection; and that it is our duty to do ſo: The ſacred Scriptures do frequently ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort us to truſt in and rely upon him, and to caſt all our care upon him, and not to doubt of his help and aſſiſtance when we ſhall ſtand in great need of it. Pſal. 62.7, 8. ſaith the Pſalmiſt; <hi>In God is my Salvation and my glory; the Rock of my ſtrength and my refuge is in God. Truſt in him at all times, ye people; pour out your heart before him: God is a refuge for us.</hi> And Pſal. 115.9— <hi>O Iſrael, truſt thou in the Lord: he is their help and their ſhield. O houſe of Aaron, truſt in the Lord: he is their help and their ſhield. Ye that fear the Lord, truſt in the Lord: he is their help and their ſhield.</hi> And in many other places in the Pſalms are we exhorted to this. And this is <hi>Solomon</hi>'s exhortation, Prov. 3.5; <hi>Truſt in the Lord with all thine heart, and lean not unto thine own underſtanding.</hi> And ſaith the Prophet Iſ. 50, 10; <hi>Who is among you that feareth the Lord, that obeyeth the voice of his ſervant, that walketh in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and hath no light? Let him truſt in the Name of the Lord, and ſtay upon his God.</hi> In all ſad and comfortleſs conditions are his Servants to have recourſe to him, and there to reſt themſelves ſecure. And this we are alſo exhorted to and enjoined by the Goſpel, to caſt all our care upon Almighty God, and to truſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely in him. 2 Cor. 1.9. <hi>But we had the ſentence of death in our ſelves</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>that we ſhould not truſt in our ſelves, but in God which raiſeth the dead.</hi> And ſaith St. <hi>Peter,</hi> 1 Pet. 5.6, 7; <hi>Humble your ſelves therefore under the mighty hand of God, that he may exalt you in due time, caſting all your care upon him, for he careth for you.</hi> And upon all accounts whatſoever are we to truſt in and rely upon Almighty God; in all wants, and in all dangers; both for the obtaining of all ſuch things as are neceſſary and need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for us, and for the avoiding of all ſuch things as are injurious and hurtful to us. And</p>
            <p n="1">1, We are to truſt in and rely upon the Lord <hi>Jehovah,</hi> the living and true God, for help and ſuccor in all the wants and needs and neceſſities that we ly and labor under at any time here in this World. We are to rely upon him for a ſupply to all our temporal wants or food and raiment, and of all other neceſſaries of this life; and not to vex and diquiet our ſelves with carking care and deſpondent
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:47917:5"/> thoughts, nor to have recourſe to any ſinful and unlawful means to furniſh our ſelves with ſuch things as we ſtand in need of. We are to uſe our own honeſt endeavours, and to call upon him for relief; and then to believe that he will ſupply us with ſuch things as we want, ſo far as he ſees it to be needful and convenient for us. And this we are more particularly exhorted to in the ſacred Scriptures, and are therein aſſured that God will ſupply us with all ſuch things as we want and have great need of. This the Pſalmiſt ſheweth, Pſal. 33.18, 19; <hi>Behold the eye of the Lord is upon them that fear him, upon them that hope in his mercy; To deliver their ſoul from death, and to keep them alive in famine.</hi> And Pſal. 34.9, 10. <hi>O fear the Lord ye his Saints; for there is no want to them that fear him. The young Lions do lack, and ſuffer hunger; but they that fear the Lord, ſhall not want any good thing.</hi> And again Pſal. 37.3, ſaith the Pſalmiſt; <hi>Trust in the Lord, and do good, ſo ſhalt thou dwell in the land, and verily thou ſhalt be fed.</hi> Thoſe that do this, need not doubt of a ſupply herein. And ſaith God by the Prophet Iſaiah, 41.17, 18; <hi>When the poor and needy ſeek water, and there is none, and their tongue faileth for thirſt; I the Lord will hear them, I the God of Iſrael will not forſake them: I will open rivers in the high pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and fountains in the midſt of the valleys; I will make the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs a pool of water, and the dry land ſprings of water.</hi> And our bleſſed Lord doth exhort us to rely upon God in this reſpect, and diſſuades us from all anxiety of mind, and carking care about the things of this world, aſſuring us that God will not fail to provide theſe things for us, if we ſerve him as we ought. Matt. 6.25—; <hi>Therefore I ſay unto you</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>take no thought for your life, what ye ſhall eat, or what ye ſhall drink; nor yet for your body, what ye ſhall put on: Is not the life more than meat? and the body than raiment? Behold the fowls of the air; for they ſow not, neither do they reap, nor gather into barns; yet your heavenly Father feedeth them. Are ye not much better than they?</hi> And ver. 28—, <hi>And why take ye thought for raiment? Conſider the lilies of the field, how they grow: they toil not, neither do they ſpin: And yet I ſay unto you, that even Solomon in all his glory was not arrayed like one of theſe. Wherefore if God ſo cloath the graſs of the field, which to day is, and to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row is caſt into the oven; ſhall he not much more cloath you, O ye of little faith? Therefore take no thought, ſaying, what ſhall we eat?
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:47917:6"/> or what ſhall we drink? or wherewithal ſhall we be cloathed? For your heavenly Father knoweth that ye have need of all theſe things. But ſeek ye firſt the Kingdom of God, and his righteouſneſs, and all theſe things ſhall be added unto you.</hi> Our bleſſed Lord here doth let us know, that God having given us life and a body, will give us alſo ſuch things as are neceſſary for the ſupporting of them; and that he well underſtands, and minds what is needful for us: And by God's care of inferior creatures, he doth aſſure us, that he will have a greater care of us, and will be ſure not to fail us herein, if we ſeek his Kingdom and the Righteouſneſs thereof. And to this purpoſe, <hi>Lu.</hi> 12.22—. And often are we exhorted by the Apoſtles to lay aſide all ſolicitous thoughts about theſe things, and to depend upon Almighty God for them. It is our duty to truſt in God in this reſpect; and if we ſhould be ſtript of all, in this dark Time that is coming upon us, we are then eſpecially to put it in practice, and to rely upon the good Providence of God; and not to doubt but that he will relieve and help us, ſo far as he ſhall ſee it to be convenient for us.</p>
            <p>And for a ſupply to all our ſpiritual wants and needs are we to rely and depend upon Almighty God. We are to make our ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt prayers to him for the aſſiſtance of his Grace and Spirit, to enable us to do our duty, and to overcome all temptations that ſhall aſſault us; and for all ſuch Graces and Virtues and other ſpiritual ſuccors that we have need of; and then to depend upon him for relief herein. And our bleſſed Lord doth aſſure us that we ſhall be ſufficiently furniſhed with divine Aſſiſtance, if we do ſo. Lu. 11.13, ſaith he; <hi>If ye then, being evil, know how to give good gifts unto your children, how much more ſhall your heavenly Father give the holy Spirit to them that aſk him?</hi> And ſaith St. James 1.5; <hi>If any of you lack wiſdom, let him aſk of God, that giveth to all men libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, and upbraideth not; and it ſhall be given him.</hi> For the bleſſed aſſiſtance of God's Spirit, and for all heavenly wiſdom and underſtanding and power to withſtand temptations, and for all other ſpiritual aid and help are we to ſeek to God, and to rely upon him for a ſupply herein; and then we ſhall be ſure to be furniſhed with a ſufficiency of them, if we ſeek them as we ought.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We are to truſt in Almighty God in all the Dangers that we at any time ſhall be expoſed to, aſſuring our ſelves that he will
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:47917:6"/> not then be wanting to us. And this is the thing which the Text ſeemeth chiefly to reſpect, as the chapter ſheweth. We are not raſhly and wilfully to run into dangers, and ſo to tempt the Lord; but in all the dangers and hazards that we are brought into by the various Revolutions and Viciſſitudes of this World, or that do any ways caſually befal us, are we to truſt in and rely upon Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God for help and deliverance. In all times of the Plague and Peſtilence, and great Sickneſs and Mortality; In all times of War and Bloodſhed and great Perſecution and Tribulation (ſuch as we are now to expect) and in all perilous and dangerous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions and circumſtances whatſoever are we to truſt in his good Providence and Protection, and to expect help and relief from him. We are not to <hi>be afraid for the terror by night, nor for the arrow that flyeth by day, nor for the peſtilence that walketh in darkneſs, nor for the deſtruction that waſteth at noon-day;</hi> Pſal. 91.5, 6. We are not ſo to be afraid of theſe, or the like, as to deſpair of mercy and help from Almighty God; but at all times and in all places where we are threatned with any dangers, we are to have recourſe to him in prayer, and then to reſt ſecurely upon his divine Help and Aſſiſtance, and to know that he will be <hi>a very preſent help in</hi> all our <hi>trouble,</hi> as the Pſalmiſt ſaith. Pſal. 46.1. And we are further aſſured of his bleſſed help at ſuch times in ſeveral other places of his ſacred word. Pſal. 91.3, ſaith the Pſalmiſt; <hi>Surely he ſhall deliver thee from the ſnare of the fowler, and from the noiſom peſtilence. He ſhall cover thee with his feathers, and under his wings ſhalt thou truſt.</hi> And God doth give his People great aſſurance of his Help and Protection when they have great need of them, by his Prophet Iſaiah, 41.10—. <hi>Fear thou not</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>for I am with thee; be not diſmayed, for I am thy God: I will ſtrengthen thee; yea, I will help thee; yea I will uphold thee with the right hand of my righteouſneſs. Behold, all they that were incenſed againſt thee ſhall be aſhamed and confounded; they ſhall be as nothing; and they that ſtrive with thee ſhall periſh. Thou ſhalt ſeek them, and ſhalt not find them, even them that contended witb thee: They that war againſt thee, ſhall be as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and as a thing of nought. For I the Lord thy God will hold thy right hand, ſaying unto thee, fear not, I will help thee</hi>—. This large exhortation and great encouragement doth God give to his People, to reſt themſelves ſecurely upon him, and not to fear their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:47917:7"/> which ſhould thus vaniſh away and come to nought. And if we firmly truſt in God, we may expect that this promiſe will be made good to us now, and that our enemies ſhall thus vaniſh and come to nought. And he promiſeth to be with his People in all the great dangers that they are brought into. Iſ. 43.2. <hi>When thou paſſeſt thorow the waters</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I will be with thee; and thorow the rivers, they ſhall not overflow thee: When thou walkeſt thorow the fire, thou ſhalt not be burnt, neither ſhall the flame kindle upon thee.</hi> And even at the Stake, (if it ſhould pleaſe God to ſuffer us to be brought thither) are we to confide and truſt in the Lord <hi>Jehovah,</hi> and to expect that even then he will be a Mighty God and Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our to us, and furniſh us with extraordinary help and ſtrength fit for ſuch a Fiery Tryal. He that hath promiſed to be with his People and Servants when they paſs thorow the fire and water, will be ſure to be ſo with them, when there ſhall be this great occaſion for his aſſiſtance. We are to truſt in the Lord for ever, and upon no account whatſoever to diſtruſt him and deſpair of his mercy and ſuccor and help.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> We may ſee that ſuch are bleſſed and happy, that place their Truſt and confidence in Almighty God, and ſecurely rely upon him; and that this will engage him the more firmly to ſuccour and protect them at all times, eſpecielly when they moſt of all want his help and aſſiſtance. This the Pſalmiſt doth often aſſert, that ſuch are bleſſed that put their Truſt in him. Pſal. 2.12; ſaith he; <hi>Bleſſed are all they that put their truſt in him.</hi> And Pſal. 34.8. <hi>O taſt and ſee that the Lord is good; bleſſed is the man that truſteth in him.</hi> And Pſal. 40.4. <hi>Bleſſed is the man, that maketh the Lord his truſt; and reſpecteth not the proud, and ſuch as go about with lyes.</hi> In theſe places doth he ſhew how bleſſed and happy ſuch men are. And ſaith Solomon, Prov. 16.20; <hi>Whoſo truſteth in the Lord, happy is he.</hi> And ſaith the Prophet Jeremiah, 17.7—; <hi>Bleſſed is the man that truſteth in the Lord, and whoſe hope the Lord is. For he ſhall be as a tree planted by the waters, and that ſprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth out her roots by the river, and ſhall not ſee when heat cometh; but her leaf ſhall be green, and ſhall not be careful in the year of drought</hi>—. He is bleſſed becauſe he ſhall find comfort and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhment when an evil Time cometh, and will not be ſo ſhaken and terrified with it as others are like to be. And in ſeveral
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:47917:7"/> places do the ſacred Scriptures ſhew what great good ſhall be to ſuch as wait and reſt upon God, and truſt in him alone. Pſal. 31.19, ſaith the Pſalmiſt; <hi>O how great is thy goodneſs, which thou haſt laid up for them that fear thee; which thou haſt wrought for them that truſt in thee, before the ſons of men!</hi> And Pſal. 32.10. <hi>Many ſorrows ſhall be to the wicked</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>but he that truſteth in the Lord; mercy ſhall compaſs him about.</hi> And Pſal. 34.22. <hi>The Lord redeemeth the ſoul of his ſervants; and none of them that truſt in him ſhall be deſolate.</hi> And Pſal. 125.1: <hi>They that truſt in the Lord ſhall be as mount Zion, which cannot he moved.</hi> The <hi>Pſalms</hi> we ſee are very full to this purpoſe, exhorting men to truſt in Almighty God, and aſſuring them that they ſhall find great benefit and advantage in ſo doing. And ſaith God by the Prophet, complaining of the infidelity of his People towards him, Iſ. 57.13; <hi>When thou cryeſt let thy companies deliver thee: but the wind ſhall carry them away; vanity ſhall take them: But he that putteth his truſt in me, ſhall poſſeſs the land, and ſhall inherit my holy Mountain.</hi> To ſuch doth he promiſe the inheritance of his land and holy Mountain, that make him their Rock and Truſt. And ſuch as ſhall now truſt in him in this great Day and dark Time that is coming upon us, I hope will now be preſerved to inherit his land here and holy Mountain.</p>
            <p>This truſting in God is that which alone muſt afford us comfort and refreſhment in the midſt of all our ſorrows ond miſeries that befall us here. And this will be ſure to do it, and will free us the moſt from all ſolicitous care and anxious thoughts about the Concerns of this World; and ſet our hearts the moſt at reſt that can be here. Such is our condition here in this World, that we ſhall always be lyable to wants and dangers, and can have no other ſecurity of freedom from them. The Revolutions of this World are ſo various and frequent, and our condition here ſo uncertain, that we muſt of neceſſity be often expoſed to an indigent condition and great hazards; and there is no ſecuring our ſelves againſt them by all the humane Arts and ſubtilty that we can uſe: For theſe are ſoon fruſtrated and ſhattered to pieces by the waves of an adverſe Fortune, and all'our hopes that depend upon them are then blaſted and come to nought. And we may ſee that no man hath ever been placed in ſuch a ſecure ſtate here, but even Kings and Emperors
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:47917:8"/> have often been reduced to great neceſſities and wants, and have often had their Lives taken away. And this ſhews that we can have ſecurity no where elſe but in Almighty God. In him we ſhall be ſure to find help in the needful time of trouble: And hereby ſhall we be the moſt freed from all anxious and perplexing thoughts before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand, and have the moſt peace and ſatisfaction of mind that can be had at ſuch a time. <hi>Jo.</hi> 16.33; ſaith our Lord; <hi>Theſe things I have ſpoken unto you, that in me ye might have peace, in the world ye ſhall have tribulation; but be of good cheer, I have overcome the world.</hi> By truſting in God we ſhall be ſure of his bleſſed and ready help, and ſhall have the peace and quiet of our minds the moſt of all ſecured that can be, and ſhall find great benefit and comfort by ſo doing; but yet we muſt not expect to be wholly freed from trouble when the evil Day cometh, nor think that the the Iniquity of the times will be any pleaſant ſpectacle to good men, but ſorrow and grief to them.</p>
            <p>To truſt and rely upon Almighty God in all times of diſtreſs and tribulation is a great act of faith towards him; and therefore will engage him the more to help and ſuccour us in all our needs and diſtreſſed conditions. By this do men ſhew to the World that they do highly honor and magnify him above all, and have great and worthy thoughts of him. Hereby they make it plainly appear to all men, that they do not take him to be a mean and deſpicable Being; that they eſteem him to be no weak and helpleſs Creature; that they look not upon him as a fallacious and deceitfull God: But that they are fully convinced that he is an Omnipotent and all-wiſe God; that they are well aſſured of his great Love and Goodneſs; that they doubt not of his Veracity and fidelity; that they dare fully rely upon his Word and Promiſes, and dare truſt him with their Lives and Souls and all that is dear to them. By truſting in Almighty God men do highly honor and magnify him, not only in their own hearts and breaſts, but alſo in the eyes of the World; And for ſuch faith and truſt in God is <hi>Abraham</hi> highly commended in the Word of God; <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. But on the other hand, he that truſteth not in him, doth greatly debaſe and Vilify him; he ſheweth that he is not a God to be truſted in, and that he dares not rely upon his Word and Promiſes, and ſo makes him an unfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful or helpleſs God, if not both; and as the Scripture ſheweth, 1 <hi>Jo.</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:47917:8"/> 5.10, doth make him a <hi>lyar.</hi> This is a great act of ſaith, to truſt in God in times of great diſtreſs and danger; and hereby (for our greater encouragement) ſhall we engage him more firmly to be our Helper and Protector, becauſe we do rely upon him. Good men do look upon themſelves to be more obliged not to fail ſuch as truſt in them, and ſome way or other rely upon them for help and aſſiſtance. And much more then, we may be ſure, will Almighty God look upon himſelf to be more obliged to help and ſuccour ſuch as firmly rely upon him alone in all their ſtraits and diſtreſſed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions. And the Sacred Scriptures do ſhew that he will be ſure to help ſuch, for this very reaſon, becauſe they do faithfully rely upon his Divine Aid and aſſiſtance, and wait upon him for it. This the Pſalmiſt ſheweth, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 37.39, 40: <hi>But the Salvation of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous is of the Lord; he is their ſtrength in the time of trouble. And the Lord ſhall help them, and deliver them; he ſhall deliver them from the wicked, and ſave them, becauſe they truſt in him.</hi> And <hi>Pſ.</hi> 91.9—. <hi>Becauſe thou haſt made the Lord, which is my refuge, even the moſt High thy habitation; There ſhall no evil befall thee; neither ſhall any Plague come nigh thy Dwelling: For he ſhall give his Angels charge over thee, to keep thee in all thy ways.</hi> And this the Prophet ſheweth here, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 26.3, the verſe before the Text; <hi>Thou wilt keep him in perfect peace, whoſe mind is ſtayed on thee, becauſe he truſteth in thee.</hi> By truſting in Almighty God, we ſee, we ſhall engage him more firmly to be a Rock of our ſalvation at all times; and he will be ſure to ſave and deliver us in his good time, becauſe we truſt in him, and wait for his almighty Aid. And, as the Pſalmiſt ſaith, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 146.5, <hi>Happy is he that hath the God of Jacob for his help, whoſe hope is in the Lord his God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> For an exhortation hereto and for our encouragement herein, we may ſee that this hath been the reſolution and practice of all good men; to truſt in the Lord in all the dangers and diſtreſſed conditions that they have been brought into. When <hi>Abraham</hi> was commanded to depart out of his own country, he obeyed, and truſted to the good Providence of God for protection and relief in all the hazardous and neceſſitous conditions that he ſhould be brought into; <hi>Gen.</hi> 12.1—; And ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.8. <hi>By faith Abraham, when he was called to go out into a place which he ſhould after receive for an inheritance, obeyed; and he went out, not
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:47917:9"/> knowing whither he went.</hi> He truſted to the good Providence of God in this Pilgrimage that he took in obedience to his command. And he always took the Promiſes of God for truth, tho' he could not ſee how they ſhould be performed: And ſo muſt we now do, if we will be his faithfull and bleſſed Children. <hi>Moſes</hi> put his truſt in God, and at his command went to redeem and deliver the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> out of the hand of a powerful King, the King of <hi>Egypt,</hi> Ex. 3—. And concerning him ſaith the Apoſtle, Heb. 11.27; <hi>By faith he forſook Egypt, not fearing the wrath of the King: for he endured as ſeeing him who is inviſible.</hi> Such was his faith and truſt in God, that he feared not the wrath of the King, but was as couragious as if he had had God viſibly by him to help and ſuccour him. And this is his encouraging Speech to the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> when they were ſore afraid being incloſed with the Sea on the one hand, and with their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies on the other: <hi>Ex.</hi> 14.13; <hi>Fear ye not, ſtand ſtill, and ſee the Salvation of the Lord, which he will ſhew to you to day; for the Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians whom ye have ſeen to day, ye ſhall ſee them again no more for ever: The Lord ſhall fight for you, and ye ſhall hold your peace.</hi> And with Faith and truſt in God Almighty did he encounter all the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions and hazards that he met with afterwards. <hi>Joſhua</hi> at God's command, and with truſt and confidence in his almighty Power and Divine Protection, went againſt all the Kings of <hi>Canaan,</hi> and did not fear to encounter and ſet upon them, when they were many of them confederated together and had united their Forces, as we may ſee <hi>Joſhua</hi> 10—. <hi>Job</hi> expreſſeth very great truſt and confidence in almighty God. <hi>Job</hi> 13.14. <hi>Wherefore</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>do I take my fleſh in my teeth, and put my life in mine hand? Tho' he ſlay me, yet will I put my truſt in him.</hi> He was reſolved ſtill to truſt in God, and to wait for his ſalvation, notwithſtanding he was in ſuch a miſerable condition that he ſeemed almoſt to be deſerted and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken of him. <hi>David</hi> alſo ſheweth what great faith and confidence he put in Almighty God. When his own Companions were ready to ſtone him, he ſtrengthened himſelf herewith. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 30.6. <hi>And David was greatly diſtreſſed; for the People ſpake of ſtoning him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſoul of all the people was grieved, every man for his Sons, and for his Daughters: but David encouraged himſelf in the Lord his God.</hi> And often in the <hi>Pſalms</hi> doth he declare his great confidence in Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God. And ſaith the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 46.1—. <hi>God is our refuge
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:47917:9"/> and ſtrength, a very preſent help in trouble. Therefore will not we fear, tho' the Earth be moved, and tho' the Mountains be carried into the midſt of the Sea; Tho' the Waters thereof roar and be troubled; tho' the Mountains ſhake with the ſwellings thereof.</hi> And <hi>Pſ.</hi> 118.6. <hi>The Lord is on my ſide, I will not fear: What can man do unto me?</hi> And ſaith the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> expreſſing his own confidence in God, as he was taught, and teaching the People alſo to do the like; <hi>Iſ.</hi> 12.2; <hi>Behold, God is my ſalvation; I will truſt and not be afraid; for the Lord JEHOVAH is my ſtrength and my Song, he alſo is become my ſalvation.</hi> The Prophet <hi>Habakkuk</hi> alſo is very full to this purpoſe, declaring how he would put his whole truſt and confidence in the Lord, and joy and rejoyce in him when all earthly comforts and ſupports were vaniſhed and taken away. <hi>Hab.</hi> 3.17, 18. <hi>Altho'</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>The Figtree ſhall not bloſſom, neither ſhall fruit be in the Vines; the labor of the Olive ſhall fail, and the field ſhall yield no meat; the flock ſhall be cut off from the fold, and there ſhall be no herd in the ſtalls: Yet I will rejoyce in the Lord, I will joy in the God of my ſalvation.</hi> The totally taking away of all theſe ſhould not make him to deſpair, but he would ſtill truſt in the Living God, and expect ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour and comfort from him. So great was the faith of the three Children that they bid defiance to <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> the great <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonian</hi> Monarch, and all that he could do; and ſlighted all his great Threats of a Fiery Furnace, aſſuring themſelves that the God of Heaven (in whom they truſted) could deliver them even out of the very jaws of Death and out of the Pit of deſtruction. <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.16—. <hi>O Nebuchadnezzar</hi> (ſay they) <hi>we are not carefull to anſwer thee in this matter. If it be ſo</hi> (that is, that thou caſt us into the fiery furnace) <hi>Our God, whom we ſerve, is able to deliver us from the burning fiery furnace, and he will deliver us out of thine hand, O King: But if not, be it known unto thee, O King, that we will not ſerve thy Gods, nor worſhip thy golden Image, which thou haſt ſet up.</hi> So little did they regard all his terrible and frightfull Threats. And with truſt and confidence in Almighty God did the Apoſtles encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all the Powers and Oppoſitions and Dangers and Neceſſities that they met with. By theſe and ſuch examples we may ſee, that this hath been the Reſolution and Practice of all pious and religious men to put their truſt in Almighty God at all times of great Danger and Need, and to rely upon him for this bleſſed Help and Aſſiſtance.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:47917:10"/> And this ſhews that it is our duty to do ſo, and is an encouragement to us to rely upon him for his never-failing Help and Succour, when we have no means of helping our ſelves, but are in a moſt helpleſs condition, as now we are like to be in.</p>
            <p n="2">II. We have here the reaſon wherewith this exhortation and precept is backed, and why we ſhould truſt in the Lord for ever; and that is becauſe of his ſure and certain Help and Aſſiſtance at all times: <hi>For in the Lord JEHOVAH is everlaſting ſtrength, or the Rock of Ages.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is an uſual thing in the Word of God to call Almighty God a Rock, becauſe he is a moſt ſure and firm Refuge to all ſuch as fly to him for ſuccour and help upon all accounts. Moſes doth often call him a Rock. <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.15. <hi>But Jeſurun waxed fat, — then he forſook God which made him, and lightly eſteemed the Rock of his ſalvation.</hi> And verſ. 31. <hi>For their Rock is not as our Rock, even our enemies themſelves being judges:</hi> Hereby meaning, that their God and Protector was not like the God that protected and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended the Jews, even in the judgment of their Enemies. And in ſeveral other places in the ſacred Scriptures is Almighty God called a Rock. And by God's being called <hi>the Rock of Ages</hi> here, we are to know, that he will be a moſt ſure and never failing Protector Deliverer and Succourer to all ſuch as have recourſe to him at any time for his divine Help and Aſſiſtance; and that there is no reaſon to doubt and deſpair of it, if we truly ſerve him, and wait upon him for it as we ought. And this I ſhall endeavor farther to ſhew by ſeveral particulars, in ſhewing that there is in him all that is requiſite to make him an Univerſal Almighty and Eternal Protector and Helper to all ſuch as truſt and confide in him. And</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> We have the greater reaſon to truſt in the Lord <hi>Jehovah</hi> the living and true God, becauſe he is Omniſcient and knows every thing. He is not a God that is ſhort ſighted and in a great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure ignorant of the Concerns of this World, or of our particular State and Condition here; for this would render him unfit for being ſo certain and ſure a Rock of our truſt and confidence in all our exigencies and dangers. But he cannot be in the leaſt thought deficient herein; becauſe he knows all things whatſoever, without all exception, that are comprehended within the compaſs of the whole World. <hi>God</hi> (ſaith St. John 1 Jo. 3.2.) <hi>is greater than our
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:47917:10"/> hearts, and knoweth all things.</hi> So univerſal is his knowledg that nothing is excluded from it.</p>
            <p>His knowledg is general and is extended to all places in the whole World. As all the parts of the whole Univerſe are the work of his hands; ſo all ly naked and open to his view. He that fills Heaven and Earth, is every where; and has all the World plain and clear before his piercing eyes. And this is often affirmed in the ſacred Scriptures. Pſal. 139.8—, ſaith the Pſalmiſt; <hi>If I aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend up into Heaven, thou art there; If I make my bed in hell, behold thou art there; If I take the wings of the morning, and dwell in the uttermoſt parts of the ſea, even there ſhall thy hand lead me, and thy right hand ſhall hold me.</hi> And ſaith the Prophet Hanani, 2 Chr. 16.9; <hi>For the eyes of the Lord run to and fro thorowout the whole earth, to ſhew himſelf ſtrong in the behalf of them whoſe heart is perfect towards him.</hi> His eyes are employed every where, and no place eſcapes them; and with this deſign too, to ſee what is needful and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to all ſuch as have a perfect heart towards him, that he may ſuccour and help them. And ſaith Solomon, Prov. 15.3; <hi>The eyes of the Lord are in every place, beholding the evil and the good.</hi> All places, tho' never ſo far diſtant and remote from one another, ly plain and open before his all-ſeeing eyes and are never abſent from them. His eyes and knowledge penetrate thro' all dark and hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den places, where ſecret works are often a hammering out, which are concealed from the eyes of the World; but are there as viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to him as if they were doing in the open light. Pſal. 139.11—. <hi>If I ſay, ſurely the darkneſs ſhall cover me</hi> (ſaith the Pſalmiſt) <hi>even the night ſhall be light about me. Yea the darkneſs hideth not from thee, but the night ſhineth as the day; the darkneſs and the light are both alike to thee.</hi> Darkneſs it ſelf will not ſecure any from his ſight and knowledg. He by his unconceivable Deity and God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head fills all places, and is every where preſent, and there is no place where any one can hide himſelf from his knowledg, as he himſelf affirms by the Prophet, Jer. 23.24: <hi>Can any hide himſelf in ſecret places, that I ſhall not ſee him, ſaith the Lord? Do not I fill heaven and earth, ſaith the Lord?</hi> There is no place that can be excluded from his eye and knowledg, becauſe there is no place whatſoever but he is there.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:47917:11"/>
            <p>And as God's knowledg is extended to all places, ſo is it alſo extended to all Creatures, and to all their works and actions, and eſpecially to all the works of mankind. There is not one of all his Creatures, whereof there are numberleſs Hoſts and Armies, that is ever without the ſight of his eyes; nor is there one action, that is done by any of them all, that eſcapes his cognizance, but he takes knowledg of it. Iſ. 40.25—. <hi>To whom then will ye liken me, or ſhall I be equal, ſaith the holy One? Lift up your eyes on high, and behold, who hath created theſe things, that bringeth out their hoſt by number, he calleth them all by names, by the greatneſs of his might, for that he is ſtrong in power, not one faileth.</hi> This perfect know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg hath he of all the Armies of his Creatures. And he is privy to all the actions that are done by them all, and to all the ſecret tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions and contrivances that are done, or a doing any where through-out the whole earth; and to all the ſecret counſels and retired thoughts and imaginations of mens hearts. <hi>His eyes are upon the ways of man, and he ſeeth all his goings;</hi> as Elihu ſaith, Job. 34.21. And ſaith the Pſalmiſt, Pſal. 94.10; <hi>He that teacheth man knowledge, ſhall not he know?</hi> Hereby ſhewing that it is impoſſible that he ſhould be ignorant. And ſaith Solomon, Prov. 5.21; <hi>For the ways of man are before the eyes of the Lord, and he pondereth all his goings.</hi> And what the ſon of Sirach ſaith to this purpoſe is very remarkable. Ecclus. 23.18—; <hi>A man that breaketh wedlock, ſaying thus in his heart, who ſeeth me? I am compaſſed about with darkneſs, the walls cover me, and no body ſeeth me, what need I to fear? The moſt High will not remember my ſins. Such a man only feareth the eyes of man, and knoweth not that the eyes of the Lord are ten thouſand times brighter than the Sun, beholding all the ways of men, and conſidering the moſt ſecret parts.</hi> So quick-ſighted is he to behold and obſerve whatſoever is done every where in the moſt ſecret and retired corners, and all the hidden practices and machinations of men. And all men's hearts and private thoughts are all plain and open to his All-ſeeing eyes. It is his preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to be the ſearcher of all men's hearts, and to know all that is therein. Deut. 31.21. ſaith God concerning the Iſraelites; <hi>For I know their imagination, which they go about even now, before I have brought them into the land which I ſw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:47917:11"/>
            <p>All things, whether paſt, preſent, or to come, are perfectly known to Almighty God. He is an everliving and eternal God; and with his eternity does his knowledg bear proportion. He who was, and is, and is to come, knows all things that may be comprehended in theſe terms. There is no ſuch thing as forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs with him; and the things that are paſt cannot be razed and expunged out of his memory; but all things that have been done from the very Creation of the World are as freſh and preſent with him, as they were in the very day and moment when they were done. <hi>For a thouſand years in thy ſight are but as yeſterday, when it is paſt; and as a watch in the night;</hi> ſaith the Pſalmiſt, Pſal. 90.4. And ſaith St. Peter, 2 Pet. 3.8; <hi>But, beloved, be not ignorant of this one thing, that one day with the Lord is as a thouſand years, and a thouſand years as one day.</hi> And ſaith St. James, Acts 15.18; <hi>Known unto God are all his works from the beginning of the world.</hi> All that has been done from the very Creation of the World remains clear and undefaced before him: And all that is to come is clearly ſeen and known by him. Things future are unknown to us, and we cannot tell what ſhall come to paſs hereafter, except it be ſome way revealed to us. But it is not ſo with God, for he hath all things, that are future and to come, plain before his eyes. This is his peculiar prerogative to have a perfect knowledge of what is to come, as the Prophet ſheweth; Iſ. 41.23. <hi>Shew the things that are to come hereafter, that we may know that ye are Gods.</hi> It is God, and God alone, that knoweth all things future; and all that ſhall be done hereafter even to the end of the World is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly ſeen and known by him. And the things too that men would do, but ſhall be prevented and ſtopt from the doing of them, are all within the reach of his ſight. He knows what they would do, if he did not reſtrain them by his grace and power, or prevent them by death. He knows all things that can be known, and his knowledge is perfect and complete in every re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect. And this, as it ought to make us the more careful what we do, becauſe it is done before the All-ſeeing eyes of God; ſo alſo will it be a very great ground of our truſt and confidence in him. For in truſting in the Lord <hi>Jehovah,</hi> we do not truſt in any blind Deity, nor in any ſenſleſs <hi>Idol,</hi> that hath eyes, but ſeeth not; nor in a Creature that is ignorant of our condition and of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:47917:12"/> the concerns of this World: But in truſting in the Lord <hi>Jehovah</hi> the living and true God, we truſt in a God that is Omniſcient and knows every thing; That perfectly underſtands all the affairs of this World, and is thorowly acquainted with our State and Condition here; That ſees and knows all our needs and wants, and the ſorrows and miſeries that we ly and labour under, and all the hazards and dangers that we at any time are in; And that hears our addreſſes and prayers which we at all times make unto him. And therefore upon this account we have the greater reaſon to place our truſt and confidence in him, and to account him the Rock of our Salvation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> He is a God of infinite Wiſdom, and prudent in all his actions and enterprizes, and therefore we have the greater reaſon to truſt and confide in him. All his actions and doings are weighed in the ballance, and grounded upon the higheſt reaſon of all, and are managed with wiſdom and counſel. He is not like the fooliſh Builder that laid his foundation upon the Sand, and to have his work overturned with every blaſt of an adverſe Fortune; nor ſo unwiſe and imprudent as to be guilty of any ſuch error, and to have any of his intentions fruſtrated and blamed. He attempts nothing but what he will bring perfectly to paſs, and his counſel ſhall ſtand; and there is no over-reaching and out-witting of him, but he at his pleaſure can over-reach all others; and therefore we have the greater cauſe to truſt in him, and rely upon him as the Rock of our confidence at all times. <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.10; <hi>To the intent</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>that now unto the Principalities and Powers in heavenly places might be known by the Church, the manifold Wiſdom of God.</hi> And this all the works of God declare, <hi>viz,</hi> that he is a God of infinite Wiſdom and underſtanding, ſo far as we are able to judg of them. The ſtupendious Frame of this viſible World, with all the admirable works therein, will abundantly manifeſt to us the wonderful Wiſdom of him that Created and Formed it; and let us underſtand a little, how unconceivable it is. If we behold the Heavens with all the Glorious Bodies thereof, the Sun Moon and Stars, with that exact o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>er and the ſteady courſes and motions that they keep; with admiration and wonder may we ſay with the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 19.1—; <hi>The Heavens declare the Glory of God, and the Firmament ſheweth his hand-work: Day unto day uttereth
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:47917:12"/> Speech, and night unto night ſheweth knowledg.</hi> And the Earth with all the numberleſs Hoſts and Armies thereof doth ſhew the ſame. The curious Frame, and Order and Government of all the Armies and Hoſts of Creatures that are upon the face of the Earth do ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly ſhew to us, that he that formed them, and diſciplines and orders them muſt be infinite, as well in Wiſdom, as in Knowledg and Power. And ſaith the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 104.24—; <hi>O Lord, how manifold are thy works! in Wiſdom haſt thou made them all</hi> —. And ſaith <hi>Solomon Pr.</hi> 3.19 —; <hi>The Lord by Wiſdom hath founded the Earth, by underſtanding hath he eſtabliſhed the Heavens; By his knowledg the Depths are broken up; and the Clouds drop down the dew.</hi> The accurate works of God do abundantly manifeſt to us his exceeding great and infinite Wiſdom. He is infinitely Wiſe of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and needeth no Counſellor to inſtruct and direct him, as the Prophet ſheweth, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 40.13 —; <hi>Who</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>hath directed the Spirit of the Lord, or being his Counſellor hath taught him? With whom took he Counſel? and who inſtructed him, and taught him in the path of judgment? and taught him knowledg, and ſhewed to him the way of underſtanding?</hi> He is all-ſufficient in this reſpect, and he alone is Wiſe, and giveth to all others Wiſdom and underſtanding as he ſees good. <hi>Job</hi> 35.10 —, ſaith <hi>Elihu</hi> there; <hi>But none ſaith, Where is God my maker, who giveth Songs in the night? Who teacheth us more than the beaſts of the Earth, and maketh us wiſer than the Fowls of Heaven.</hi> And ſaith the Preacher, <hi>Ecc.</hi> 2.26; <hi>For God giveth to a man that is good in his ſight, wiſdom and knowledg and joy.</hi> He is the original and fountain of all Wiſdom, and there is no Wiſdom nor Counſel can prevail againſt him. There is no circumventing and over-reaching and out-witting of him: There is no craft nor policy that will ſignify any thing againſt him. <hi>The fooliſhneſs of God is wiſer than men,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.25. And ſaith <hi>Job</hi> 9.4; <hi>He is wiſe in heart, and mighty in ſtrength; who hath hardened himſelf againſt him, and hath proſpered?</hi> And ſaith <hi>Solomon, Pr.</hi> 21.30. <hi>There is no wiſdom, nor underſtanding, nor Counſel againſt the Lord.</hi> All the wiſdom and Counſel that is ſet againſt God, is like to be blaſted and to come to nought; and they that travel with Plots and Deſigns againſt him will be ſure to bring forth their own wo and miſery in the end. For he deſtroyeth the wiſdom of the wiſe, and overthroweth their Counſels at his pleaſure. He confounds all the Wit and Cunning of the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:47917:13"/> crafty, and turns it into ſtark folly and ſottiſhneſs as he ſees good. <hi>He leadeth Counſellors away ſpoiled</hi> (ſaith <hi>Job.</hi> 12.17—) <hi>and maketh judges fools.</hi> And ver. 20. <hi>He removeth away the Speech of the truſty, and taketh away the understanding of the aged.</hi> And ver. 24, 25. <hi>He taketh away the heart of the chief of the People of the Earth, and cauſeth them to wander in a Wilderneſs, where there is no way: They grope in the dark without light, and he maketh them to ſtagger like a drunken man.</hi> Thus doth he darken and confound their reaſon and underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and makes them to become like fools and mad men at his own pleaſure. And ſaith God by the Prophet, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 44.25. <hi>That fruſtrateth the tokens of the lyars, and maketh Diviners mad; that turneth wiſe men backward, and maketh their knowledg fooliſh.</hi> And ſaith the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.19.; <hi>For it is written, I will deſtroy the wiſdom of the wiſe, and will bring to nothing the underſtanding of the prudent.</hi> And again ſaith he, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.19. <hi>For the wiſdom of this World is fooliſhneſs with God: for it is written, he taketh the wiſe in their own craftineſs.</hi> Thus are they taken with their own Wit and Cunning, and their craft and policy is all retorted and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned back upon themſelves, and they do only plot and conſult for their own downfall and ruin that ſet themſelves againſt him. And now, ſeeing God is ſo unconceivably and infinitely Wiſe in all that he takes in hand, and is guilty of no errors nor over-ſights in what he doth, but acteth always like himſelf, like an All-wiſe God, and is ſure to bring his purpoſes and deſigns to perfection; ſeeing he cannot be over-reached and out-witted by either men or Devils, and that there is no counſel will ſtand good againſt him; ſeeing all the wiſdom of others is but folly with him, and he taketh the wiſe in their own craftineſs, and confoundeth the counſels and policy of the Subtle, and returneth them upon themſelves at his own plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; This will be a farther ground of our truſt and confidence that we are to repoſe and put in him. In truſting in him, we truſt not in a fooliſh and unadviſed Perſon, that undertakes ſuch a Charge that he does not well underſtand, and is not wiſe enough to manage and protect: But in truſting in the Lord <hi>Jehovah,</hi> we truſt in a God that is infinitely wiſe in all reſpects, and knows how to manage all the Charges and Cares of an univerſal Patron and Protector; and is ſuch a God for wiſdom, to whom we may well commit the care of our Souls and Lives and all that is pretious and dear to us.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:47917:13"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> He is a God that is Omnipotent and Almighty and can do every thing, and therefore we have the greater reaſon to truſt and confide in him. He is no weak and and impotent creature, but a God that is armed with all the Might and Power that can be, and therefore we may well account him the Rock of our Salvation. I am <hi>the Almighty God</hi> (ſaith he to <hi>Abraham, Gen.</hi> 17.1.) <hi>walk before me, and be thou perfect.</hi> And in theſe two reſpects eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially may God be ſaid to be Almighty.</p>
            <p n="1">1, Becauſe all Rule and all Dominion and Power of Governing all things doth in a moſt abſolute manner belong to him. He is the great and only Monarch of all the World, and all the Armies and Hoſts of Heaven and Earth are under his Authority and Power, and at his abſolute command. He is the Supreme Lord of all, and all the Angels above, and the Powers of Darkneſs, and all Earthly Kings and Princes are but his Miniſters and Servants, and muſt all obſerve his Orders and obey his word and command. <hi>For the Lord your God</hi> (ſaith <hi>Moſes Deut.</hi> 10.17.) <hi>is God of Gods, and Lord of Lords, a great God, a mighty and a terrible, which regardeth not perſons, nor taketh reward.</hi> And ſaith St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.15; <hi>Who is the bleſſed and only Potentate, the King of Kings, and Lord of Lords.</hi> He is the Supreme King over all the Kings and Emperors of the Earth; and as he ſees fit he exerciſeth his Authority and Power in all the Kingdoms of the Earth, and placeth and diſplaceth all Kings and Princes as he ſees good. This the Prophet <hi>Daniel</hi> ſheweth, <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.17. <hi>To the intent</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that the living may know, that the moſt High ruleth in the Kingdom of men, and giveth it to whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he will, and ſetteth up over it the baſeſt of men.</hi> And ver. 25, ſaith he to <hi>Nebuchadnezzar; They ſhall drive thee from men, and thy Dwelling ſhall be with the Beasts of the Field till thou know that the moſt High ruleth in the Kingdom of men, and giveth it to whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he will.</hi> And ſaith he, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.20 —; <hi>Bleſsed be the Name of God for ever and ever; for wiſdom and might are his: And he changeth the times and the Seaſons; he removeth Kings, and he ſetteth up Kings.</hi> And ſo ſaith the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 75.6 —; <hi>For pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion cometh neither from the Eaſt, nor from the Weſt, nor from the South; But G d is the Judge: he putteth down one, and ſetteth up another.</hi> He diſpoſeth of the Kingdoms of the World, and ordereth whom he pleaſeth to rule therein; and there is no man can have any
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:47917:14"/> Power therein, except it be given, or ſome ways granted and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed him from above, as our bleſſed Lord told <hi>Pilate,</hi> Joh. 19.11; <hi>Jeſus anſwered, Thou couldeſt have no power at all againſt me, except it were given thee from above.</hi> No Man can have any Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, except it be ſome way allowed him by Almighty God, who is the Supreme King and Diſpoſer of all Power and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. And he is an everlaſting King, and his Dominion is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out end, and endureth to all Eternity. <hi>Jer.</hi> 10.10; ſaith the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet there; <hi>But the Lord is the true God, he is the living God, and an everlasting King; at his wrath the earth ſhall tremble, and the Nations ſhall not be able to abide his indignation.</hi> And ſaith the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145.13; <hi>Thy Kingdom is an everlaſting Kingdom, and thy Dominion endureth throughout all generations.</hi> There is no end of his Kingdom, and his ſupreme Power endureth for ever.</p>
            <p n="2">2, God is Almighty in regard of his infinite Power, whereby he is able to effect and bring all things to paſs. He is Almighty in Operation, and there is nothing too hard for him, which he cannot do; and therefore he may be ſaid to be Omnipotent. He hath all power of doing whatſoever he pleaſeth; and all the Power and Strength that is in all Creatures is derived from him, and hath continual dependance upon him, and in this reſpect he may well be ſaid to be Almighty. It is in him that <hi>we all live, and move, and have our being,</hi> as the Apoſtle affirmeth, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.28: And there is no reſiſting and withſtanding of his Power, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can hinder him from doing any thing that he pleaſeth to do. <hi>For the Lord of Hoſts hath purpoſed</hi> (ſaith the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 14.27.) <hi>and who ſhall diſanul it? and his hand is ſtretched out, and who ſhall turn it back?</hi> And ſaith God by him, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 43.13; <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the day was, I am he, and there is none that can deliver out of mine hand; I will work, and who ſhall let it?</hi> There is no reſiſting and withſtanding of him, but all muſt truckle and give way to his Omnipotent Power. And ſaith God to <hi>Abraham, Gen.</hi> 18.14; <hi>Is any thing too hard for the Lord?</hi> hereby declaring that all things are poſſible and feaſible to him. And this doth <hi>Job</hi> acknowledg, Job 42 2; <hi>I know that thou canſt do every thing, and that no thought can be withholden from thee.</hi> And ſaith the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah</hi> 32.17; <hi>Ah Lord God, behold thou haſt made the Heaven and the Earth by thy great Power, and ſtretched out Arm, and there is nothing too
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:47917:14"/> hard for thee.</hi> And the Angel declared this to the bleſſed Virgin. <hi>Luc.</hi> 1.37; <hi>For with God nothing ſhall be unpoſſible,</hi> ſaith he. And this our Lord ſheweth, <hi>Matth.</hi> 19.26; <hi>But Jeſus beheld them, and ſaid unto them, with men this is unpoſſible, but with God all things are poſſible.</hi> He can turn and change every thing at his own will and pleaſure. He can create and form things that are not, out of nothing; and annihilate thoſe that be, and let them return to nothing again. All things that thwart not his juſtice goodneſs and truth he can do. And his power is an eternal power, and will never fail nor decay. He is an everliving God, and his Arm and Power will never be ſhortened nor diminiſhed. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.20, ſaith St. <hi>Paul; For the inviſible things of him from the creation of the world are clearly ſeen, being underſtood by the things that are made, even his eternal Power and Godhead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But we ſhall the better underſtand this Almighty Power of God, if we conſider and call to mind the wonderful works that he hath done. The ſtupendious Acts that he hath already done will let us underſtand that his Power is infinite, and too great to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended by our ſhallow capacities. His works of Creation are moſt admirable and aſtoniſhing. That he ſhould create and form the Heaven and the Earth (which is ſo often celebrated of him, to his Honour and Glory by ſuch as have had a true veneration for him) and make all this viſible World of things that did not appear and had no being: That he ſhould cauſe the Light to ſhine out of darkneſs, and divide the day and night aſunder: That he ſhould diſpoſe the World into this beautiful order, and hang the Earth upon nothing but airy Pillars: That he ſhould form and make ſuch an innumerable number of glorious Lights above, and ſuch a vaſt multitude of creatures here upon Earth: Theſe are wonderful things which we may well admire, and had hardly known, had not God by his Spirit declared them to us. The Earth, though it be ſo vaſt a body, and ſo many thouſand miles about, yet is managed and ordered by God's Almighty Power. The Sun, though a bigger body than the Earth; and all other the celeſtial bodies, though innumerable, are all guided and ordered by his Omnipotent Power. Theſe are ſo wonderful that God might well demand, as he doth of <hi>Job,</hi> chap. 38.33; <hi>Knoweſt thou the ordinances of Heaven? Canſt thou ſet the dominion
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:47917:15"/> thereof in the earth?</hi> He it is that hath commanded the morning of old, <hi>and cauſed the day ſpring to know his place.</hi> By his order and conduct <hi>the Sun ariſeth and goeth down, and haſteth to the place of his riſing again.</hi> He ſpreadeth <hi>out the heaven like a curtain, and maketh the cloud a garment for the waters. Out of whoſe womb,</hi> but his, <hi>came the ice? and the hoary froſt of heaven, who,</hi> but he, <hi>hath gendered it?</hi> ver. 29. He cauſeth the Clouds to ride in the Air, and at his command they water the face of the Earth. The ſnow cometh out of his treaſure, and he hath made a way for the lightning and thunder. The Earth is ſupported and upheld by his Almighty Power, and he bringeth forth all trees and herbs for the ſervice of Man and Beaſt.</p>
            <p>And as God's Almighty Power is declared in the works of Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation and Nature (which we the leſs admire, becauſe they are common to us) ſo is it alſo ſhewed in his ſupernatural works, and the miracles that he hath done. He can ſuſpend and ſtop the courſe of Nature, and change and alter it as he pleaſeth; and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten hath he done ſo. When God hath ſome remarkable thing to do, the Sun and Moon muſt wait the doing of it, and ſtay till it be done: And ſo we ſee that God ſtopt them in <hi>Joſhua</hi>'s days. Joſh. 10.12—; <hi>Sun ſtand thou ſtill upon Gibeon, and thou Moon in the valley of Ajalon. And the Sun ſtood ſtill, and the Moon ſtayed until the people had avenged themſelves upon their enemies—. So the Sun ſtood ſtill in the midſt of heaven, and haſted not to go down a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout a whole day.</hi> And the Sun did not only ſtand ſtill, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn back too when God commanded it, as we ſee that it did for a ſign to King <hi>Hezekiah;</hi> Iſ. 38.8: <hi>So the ſun returned ten de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, by which degrees it was gone down.</hi> Nay farther, when God the Son did ſuffer, to ſhew the blackneſs of that Crime in putting of him to death<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the light thereof was wholly taken away. Lu. 23.44 —. <hi>And it was about the ſixth hour</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Luke) and there was darkneſs over all the Earth until the ninth hour; and the ſun was darkened</hi>—. The wonders that God wrought in <hi>Egypt;</hi> the turning of their waters into blood, the hail mingled with fire, and the darkneſs that might be felt, are ſo many proofs of his great Power and Might. When his People wanted a light, he guided them by a pillar of fire; And when they wanted a way, he divided the Rea-ſea and made the waters to ſtand on an heap,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:47917:15"/> and made them a way that they might paſs through; <hi>Ex.</hi> 13 and 14 chap. By his great Power he clave the hard Rock, and cauſed waters to come forth to quench the thirſt of his People; and rained down Manna from Heaven for their food in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs. He can reſtrain the rage and violence of fire, and keep it from doing any harm; and he preſerved the three Children from being ſo much as ſcorched in the midſt of a fiery furnace, <hi>Dan.</hi> 3. He is a God, <hi>which removeth the mountains, and they know not; which overturneth them in his anger: which ſhaketh the earth out of her place, and the pillars thereof tremble;</hi> Job. 9.5, 6. He it is that killeth, and maketh alive; he bringeth down to the grave, and raiſeth up again, and there is none that can deliver out of his hand, as he ſaith, Deut. 32 39. <hi>See now that I, even I am he, and there is no God with me; I kill, and I make alive; I wound, and I heal; neither is there any that can deliver out of mine hand.</hi> And ſaith he by the Prophet Iſaiah, 43.13: <hi>Yea before the day was I am he, and there is none can deliver out of my hand.</hi> And this <hi>Balaam</hi> the great <hi>Sooth-ſayer</hi> was ſenſible of when he ſaid to <hi>Balak</hi> King of <hi>Moab</hi> that ſent for him to curſe <hi>Iſrael;</hi> Num 23.8; <hi>How ſhall I curſe, whom God hath not curſed? Or how ſhall I defie, whom the Lord hath not defied?</hi> He ſhews that it was not in his power to curſe or hurt, till God had given way for him to do ſo. Thoſe whom he bleſſeth, muſt be bleſſed; and thoſe whom he curſeth, muſt be curſed, and all the power of Men and Devils cannot hinder what he will have done. And Satan himſelf the grand Engineer of darkneſs could not touch <hi>Job,</hi> nor his Subſtance till God gave him leave, for the exerciſe and tryal of his patience. <hi>Job</hi> 1—. There is no protecting and ſaving of thoſe, whom he will deſtroy; and there is no killing, nor wounding and hurting of thoſe that he is minded to protect and ſave. There is no want of any power in him, but he is armed with all the Power and Might that can be in all reſpects. And ſeeing God hath this uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Power over all Creatures, both Men and Angels and all other Creatures; and is able to do ſuch mighty works, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he pleaſeth, and there is no reſiſting of his Power; And ſeeing this Omnipotent Power of his is Eternal and will never decay nor be diminiſhed, we may well then truſt in him at all times. In truſting in the Lord Jehovah we ſee that we do not
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:47917:16"/> vainly place our confidence in an impotent and helpleſs Deity, that has no power at all to help and ſuccour us: But in truſting in him, we truſt in the Rock of Ages, in a God that is armed with all Power and Might, and to whom nothing is impoſſible; and in one that is able to help and ſuccour us in all our needs and wants, and to ſave and defend us in all our ſtraits and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers whatſoever, and to preſerve and bring us to the enjoyment of his Eternal Kingdom in the World to come; And therefore we may well truſt and rely upon him at all times.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> The Lord <hi>Jehovah</hi> is a God of love and goodneſs, and tender and compaſſionate of us; and therefore we have the greater cauſe to truſt and confide in him at all times. His great love and goodneſs will be a farther aſſurance to us that he will be a Rock of Salvation to us in all our ſtraits and dangers. He is a God of Love, and taketh pleaſure and delight in all the works of goodneſs and mercy, and is kind and benign to all his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and deſireth the good and proſperity of them all, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally of all Mankind. This St. <hi>John</hi> affirmeth, that God is love. 1 Jo. 4.8. <hi>He that loveth not, knoweth not God</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>for God is love.</hi> And ſo again ver. 16. And this ſhews how full of love and goodneſs he is, as if this were all in all. And his love and goodneſs is diffuſed abroad like the light of the Sun, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated to all his Creatures. Pſal. 145.9. <hi>The Lord is good to all</hi> (ſaith the Pſalmiſt) <hi>and his tender mercies are over all his works.</hi> And to this purpoſe, <hi>Wiſd.</hi> 11.24; <hi>For thou loveſt all the things that are, and abhorreſt nothing which thou haſt made; for never wouldeſt thou have made any thing, if thou hadſt hated it.</hi> His love is univerſal and extended to all his works; and there is none of his numerous Off-ſpring and Creatures but ſhall ſhare therein, till they exclude themſelves from it by their wilful tranſgreſſions and provocations, and ſin againſt him with a high hand. And for all his Creatures doth he provide and take care, and feeds them all. This the Pſalmiſt ſheweth, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 104.27—; <hi>Theſe wait all upon thee, that thou mayeſt give them their meat in due ſeaſon: That thou giveſt them, they gather: thou openeſt thy hand, they are filled with good.</hi> And Pſal. 145.15—; <hi>The eyes of all wait upon thee,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and thou giveſt them their meat in due ſeaſon. Thou openeſt thine hand, and ſatisfyest the deſire of every living thing.</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:47917:16"/> All his Creatures do experience his great goodneſs; and more eſpecially doth Man do ſo. Our high Creation, and the rich preparations that he hath here made for us, do ſhew how full of love and goodneſs he is towards us. And upon this account doth the Royal Pſalmiſt cry out with admiration, Pſal. 8.4—; <hi>What is man, that thou art mindful of him? and the ſon of man, that thou viſiteſt him? For thou haſt made him a little lower than the Angels, and haſt crowned him with glory and honor. Thou madeſt him to have dominion over the works of thy hands; thou haſt put all things under his feet.</hi> And he proclaimed himſelf a gracious and merciful God to <hi>Moſes;</hi> Exod. 34.6; <hi>And the Lord paſſed by before him, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed, The Lord, the Lord God merciful and gracious, long-ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and abundant in goodneſs and truth</hi>—. And this the Pſalmiſt doth often declare. Pſal. 86.15. <hi>But thou, O Lord, art a God full of compaſſion and gracious, long-ſuffering, and plenteous in mercy and truth.</hi> And Pſal. 103.8. <hi>The Lord is merciful and gracious, ſlow to anger, and plenteous in mercy.</hi> And to this purpoſe in ſeveral o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places. And ſaith God by the Prophet Jeremiah 9.24—; <hi>I am the Lord, which exerciſe loving kindneſs judgment and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs in the earth; for in theſe things I delight, ſaith the Lord.</hi> Theſe are the things wherein he delighteth and taketh pleaſure. And this was the Prophet <hi>Jonah</hi>'s reply to God, when he ſpared <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niveh,</hi> Jonah 4.2; <hi>For I knew that thou art a gracious God and mercifull, ſlow to Anger, and of great kindneſs, and repenteſt thee of the evil.</hi> And ſaith St. <hi>Paul, Eph.</hi> 2, 4.5; <hi>But God, who is rich in mercy, for his great love, wherewith he loved us; even when we were Dead in ſins</hi>—. By theſe and many more places are we taught how full of love, and all manner of goodneſs our God and great Creator is. He is no cruel and mercileſs Being, that knows not what belongs to love and goodneſs; but a God of infinite love and kindneſs, and is greatly delighted in doing acts of mercy and beneficence to all mankind: For he doth not onely ſhew himſelf kind to the good, but alſo to the evil, as our Lord hath told us; <hi>Matt.</hi> 5.45.</p>
            <p>And we may ſee that he is a God of great pity and mercy, and tender of his People in all their ſorrows and miſeries. He takes no delight to ſee them miſerable, and to labor and groan under any Affliction and Calamity, but is troubled for them, and is then forward to help them; and therefore we have the greater
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:47917:17"/> cauſe to rely upon him. <hi>Like as a father pitieth his children</hi> (ſaith the Pſalmiſt, 103.13—.) <hi>ſo the Lord pitieth them that fear him. For he knoweth our frame, he remembereth that we are duſt.</hi> He conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth our weak and frail nature, and what need we have of ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour and relief, and doth pity us as a Father doth his tender and helpleſs child. His bowels will always yearn towards his Servants, whenſoever they are in any afflicted and ſuffering condition; and he will then pity and help them. Pſal. 12.5. <hi>For the oppreſſion of the poor, for the ſighing of the needy, now will I ariſe (ſaith the Lord) I will ſet him in ſafety from him that puffeth at him.</hi> And ſaith he to Moſes, Ex. 3.7—; <hi>I have ſurely ſeen the affliction of my people which are in Egypt, and I have heard their cry, by reaſon of their taſk-maſters, for I know their ſorrows; and I am come down to deliver them out of the hand of the Egyptians</hi>—. Thus did God pity them, and was moved with their ſorrow and miſery, and redeemed them with a mighty hand and out-ſtretched arm. And ſaith the Prophet Zechariah 2.8; <hi>For he that toucheth you, toucheth the apple of his eye.</hi> So tender is he of his People. And though the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> did often rebel againſt him, yet ſo prone is he to mercy and pity, that he was ready to help and ſuccour them, whenſoever they returned<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and cryed to him for mercy and help. This we may ſee, Judges 10.15—; <hi>And the children of Iſrael ſaid unto the Lord, we have ſinned, do thou unto us whatſoever ſeemeth good unto thee; deliver us only, we pray thee, this day. And they put away the ſtrange Gods from among them, and ſerved the Lord; and his ſoul was grieved for the miſery of Iſrael.</hi> And ſaith the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt, Pſal. 106.44—; <hi>Nevertheleſs he regarded their affliction, when he heard their cry. And he remembered for them his covenant, and repented according to the multitude of his mercies. He made them alſo to be pitied of all thoſe that carried them captives.</hi> He cannot ſhew himſelf hard-hearted towards his People, when they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent and cry to him for ſuccour and help. He that is the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of mercies, will not then ſtop his ears at their cry, but will then hear and help them, and ſhew them mercy and kindneſs. By theſe and ſuch places we ſee that he is full of pity and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, and takes no delight to ſee his People miſerable, but does greatly commiſerate them in their diſtreſs and ſorrow, and is forward to help them; and this will give us greater encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:47917:17"/> to truſt and rely upon him as the Rock of our Salvation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> For our greater aſſurance, we may ſee that he is not only a God of love and goodnes, but that he doth undertake our protection, and is engaged by promiſe to ſuccor and help us in all our troubles and diſtreſſed conditions, if we ſerve him and obey him as we ought; and therefore we have the greateſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of all to truſt and confide in him at all times. He is a God of truth, and faithful in all his promiſes; and he hath promiſed that he will always watch over us, and take great care to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, and keep us; and therefore we have no reaſon to doubt of his protection and help, if we faithfully ſerve him as we ſhould. This <hi>Balaam</hi> declared, that God was true and faithfull and would make good what he had promiſed. Num. 23.19. <hi>God</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is not a man, that he ſhould ly; neither the ſon of man, that he ſhould repent: hath he ſaid, and ſhall he not do it? or hath he ſpoken, and ſhall he not make it good?</hi> And St. <hi>Paul</hi> declareth the ſame to <hi>Titus;</hi> Tit. 1.2; <hi>In hope of eternal life, which God, that cannot ly, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed before the world began,</hi> And ſaith <hi>Moſes,</hi> Deut. 7.9; <hi>Know therefore that the Lord thy God, he is God, the faithful God, which keepeth covenant and mercy with them that love him, and keep his commandments, to a thouſand generations.</hi> He is a God of veracity and truth, and will not fail to make good his promiſes; And he hath promiſed that he will never fail nor forſake all ſuch as fear him, and keep his ſacred Commandments. This <hi>Moſes</hi> told the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> when they were to encounter and engage with their enemies. Deut. 31.6. <hi>Be ſtrong and of a good courage</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>fear not, nor be afraid of them; for the Lord thy God he it is that doth go with thee; he will not fail thee, nor forſake thee.</hi> And ſaith the Apoſtle, Heb. 13.5; <hi>For he hath ſaid, I will never leave thee, nor forſake thee.</hi> And this is God's command that we ſhould call upon him in the time of trouble, and he doth promiſe that he will then deliver us, Pſal. 50.15. <hi>And call upon me in the day of trouble; I will deliver thee, and thou ſhalt glorify me.</hi> And God doth give his People great aſſurance of his Help and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection in all times of need and danger by the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah.</hi> Iſ. 43.2— ſaith he; <hi>When thou paſſeſt thorow the waters, I will be with thee; and thorow the rivers, they ſhall not overflow thee; when thou walkeſt thorow the fire, thou ſhalt not be burnt; neither ſhall the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:47917:18"/> flame kindle upon thee: For I am the Lord thy God, the holy One of Iſrael.</hi> This great and gracious promiſe doth God make to his People of being their mighty Protector and Saviour in all great and eminent dangers. And ſaith he again by the Prophet, Iſ. 54.16—; <hi>Behold, I have created the ſmith that bloweth the coals in the fire, and that bringeth forth an inſtrument for his work; and I have created the waſter to deſtroy. No weapon that is formed againſt thee ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper; and every tongue that ſhall riſe againſt thee in judgment, thou ſhalt condemn.</hi> Both the weapons of War, and the waſter that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroys are at God's command; and ſhall not prevail farther than he gives them leave; And he doth promiſe that they ſhall not proſper ſo far as to deſtroy his Church and Servants, though he may ſometimes let wicked men put ſome of his Servants to death for a teſtimony of the Truth; with whom he will then be in an extraordinary manner by his Grace and Spirit, that they ſhall in a manner even then triumph over them. And ſaith our Saviour, Matt. 28.20; <hi>And lo, I am with you alway, even unto the end of the world; Amen.</hi> And we may be ſure that he will be with us according to our needs, and in an extraordinary manner when there is extraordinary occaſion for it. By theſe and ſuch places we ſee that God doth undertake our protection, and doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to help and defend us in all our ſtraits and dangers. And a watchful care hath he over us at all times, as we have ſeen before. 2 Chr. 16.9. <hi>For the eyes of the Lord run to and fro tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row out the whole earth</hi> (ſaith Hanani the Seer) <hi>to ſhew himſelf ſtrong in the behalf of them, whoſe heart is perfect towards him.</hi> And ſaith the Pſalmiſt, Pſal. 121.3—; <hi>He will not ſuffer thy foot to be moved; he that keepeth thee will not ſlumber; Behold, he that keepeth Iſrael ſhall neither ſlumber nor ſleep. The Lord is thy keeper; the Lord is thy ſhade upon thy right hand.</hi> He con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually watches over ſuch as fear him, and is never unmindful and regardleſs of them. And how exceedingly his mind is bent towards them, and how much his heart is ſet upon them, he ſheweth by the Prophet Iſaiah, 49.15: <hi>Can a woman forget her ſucking child</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that ſhe ſhould not have compaſſion on the ſon of her womb? Yea they may forget; yet will I not forget thee.</hi> So mindful and careful will he be of all his faithful Servants. And his Angels ſhall watch about ſuch, as the Pſalmiſt affirmeth, Pſal.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:47917:18"/> 34.7; <hi>The Angel of the Lord encampeth round about them that fear him, and delivereth them.</hi> With ſuch a watchful Gard are they always encompaſſed and protected. And to ſhew the exquiſite care of God concerning all things and even the ſmalleſt matters that belong to us, our Saviour hath told us that the very hairs of our heads are numbered. Matt. 10.30. <hi>But even the very hairs of your head are all numbered: Fear ye not therefore</hi>—. A due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard is had even to the ſmalleſt matters that belong to us. And the Apoſtle doth ſhew that nothing can ſeparate us from the love of God, if we do it not by our own wickedneſs. Rom. 8.38—. <hi>For I am perſuaded</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that neither death, nor life, nor An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, nor Principalities, nor Powers, nor things preſent, nor things to come, nor height, nor depth, nor any other creature ſhall be able to ſeparate us from the love of God, which is in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord.</hi> We are aſſured of God's truth and faithfulneſs; and we ſee that he hath engaged and promiſed to be our Protector and Helper in all our neceſſities and dangers, and that he doth continually watch over us and mind us; and therefore there is no reaſon to doubt of his Almighty aid and help in all our needs and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers whatſoever, if we are careful to ſerve and pleaſe him as we ought.</p>
            <p>But ſo long as we go on in a ſinful courſe, he is not obliged to be our Protector and Defender. By going on in a wicked courſe of life without repentance, we put our ſelves from under his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, and cauſe him to caſt of his care of us: For he hath engaged himſelf to be a Rock and Shield only to ſuch as fear him and keep his Commandments. This is manifeſt from ſeveral places before mentioned. He ſheweth <hi>himſelf ſtrong,</hi> but it is <hi>in behalf of thoſe, whoſe heart is perfect towards him;</hi> 2 Chr. 16.9. And ſaith St. <hi>Peter,</hi> 1 Pet. 3.12; <hi>For the eyes of the Lord are over the righteous, and his ears are open unto their prayers: but the face of the Lord is againſt them that do evil.</hi> Such as do evil and go on in a wicked courſe, are not to expect his care and watchful Providence to attend them for good, but have cauſe to expect the contrary, and are to know that God will not then be their Protector and Helper, but their Adverſary. But if ſuch repent and return unto the Lord, and reſolve for the future to keep his ſacred Commandments, he is gracious and prone to mercy, and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:47917:19"/> will then pardon them, and receive them into his care and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection. Iſaiah 55.7. <hi>Let the wicked forſake his way, and the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous man his thoughts, and let him return unto the Lord, and he will have mercy upon him; and to our God, for he will abundantly pardon.</hi> He will be reconciled to ſinners, if they will repent and return to him, and will then become their mighty God and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector, and will then ſave and help them, as we ſee he did the <hi>Jews,</hi> when they returned and cryed to him for help; Jud. 10.15—. If men do ſerve him as they ought, or will return and become obedient to him, he will be a moſt ſure Helper and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Protector to them, and there is no cauſe that they ſhould doubt of his help and ſuccour at any time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> The extraordinary and miraculous deliverances that God hath wrought for his People and Servants in their ſtraits and diſtreſſed conditions, when they have had little or no means of helping themſelves, will be a farther encouragement to us to rely and depend upon him for help and ſuccour at all times, when we have no power to help and relieve our ſelves. Seeing God hath ſtretched out his Almighty Arm to defend and help his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants in times paſt, we may the more chearfully hope that he will do the like for us now in our great need and helpleſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, if we ſerve him as we ought, and rely upon his mercy and goodneſs for protection and relief: For his Arm is not ſhorte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that it cannot ſave; nor will he now be more backward to do it than he hath been heretofore. And many and great delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances and extraordinary Succours and Supports hath God vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed to his People and Servants when there hath been occaſion for ſuch, ſome whereof I ſhall here mention.</p>
            <p n="1">1, God hath often relieved his Servants and People in their wants and neceſſities in a wonderful manner with food and ſuch things as they ſtood in need of. He gave the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> Manna and Quails in the wilderneſs when they wanted food, and began to murmur againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron.</hi> Exod. 16.12. <hi>I have heard the murmurings of the children of Iſrael</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>ſpeak unto them ſaying; at even ye ſhall eat fleſh, and in the morning ye ſhall be filled with bread, and ye ſhall know that I am the Lord your God.</hi> And for forty years together did he feed them with Manna in the wilderneſs where they wanted food, untill
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:47917:19"/> they came into a land that had food ſufficient for them. And he cauſed their garments not to wax old in all this time, that they might not want raiment, as <hi>Moſes</hi> tells them; <hi>Deut.</hi> 8.4. <hi>Thy raiment waxed not old upon thee, neither did thy foot ſwell theſe forty years.</hi> And when they wanted water, he brought them water out of the rock. Numb. 20.8. <hi>Take the rod</hi> (ſaith God to <hi>Moſes) and gather thou the aſſembly together, thou and Aaron thy brother, and ſpeak ye unto the rock before their eyes; and it ſhall give forth his water, and thou ſhalt bring forth to them water out of the rock; ſo thou ſhalt give the congregation and their beaſts drink.</hi> And ver. 11. <hi>And Moſes lift up his hand, and with his rod he ſmote the rock twice; and the water came out abundantly, and the congregation drank, and their beaſts alſo.</hi> God gave <hi>Samſon</hi> water in his great thirſt, <hi>Judg.</hi> 15.18—. And he commanded the ravens to feed the Prophet <hi>Elijah,</hi> and they did ſo: 1 Kings 17.2—. <hi>And the word of the Lord came unto him, ſaying, Get thee hence, and turn thee eaſtward, and hide thy ſelf by the brook Cherith, that is before Jordan. And it ſhall be, that thou ſhalt drink of the brook, and I have commanded the ravens to feed thee there. So he went, and did according unto the word of the Lord: for he went and dwelt by the brook Cherith, that is before Jordan. And the ravens brought him bread and fleſh in the morning, and bread and fleſh in the evening; and he drank of the brook.</hi> And after this was he and the Widow Woman of <hi>Zarephath</hi> and her Houſe ſuſtained many days with a handful of meal and a little oyl, at God's command, when the famine was great in the land. ver. 13—. <hi>And Elijah ſaid unto her, fear not; go and do as thou hast ſaid; but make me thereof a little cake firſt, and bring it unto me; and after make for thee, and for thy ſon. For thus ſaith the Lord God of Iſrael, The barrel of meal ſhall not waſt, neither ſhall the cruſe of oyl fail, until the day that the Lord ſendeth rain upon the earth. And ſhe went, and did according to the ſaying of Elijah; and ſhe and he and her houſe did eat many days. And the barrel of meal waſted not, neither did the cruſe of oyl fail</hi>—. And when he fled from <hi>Jezebel,</hi> and was in the Wilderneſs beyond <hi>Beerſheba</hi> in a deſtitute condition, the Angel of the Lord brought him a cake and water to ſupport and ſtrengthen him. 1 Kings 19.5—. <hi>And as he lay and ſlept under a juniper-tree, behold then an
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:47917:20"/> Angel touched him, and ſaid unto him, Ariſe and eat. And he looked, and behold, there was a cake baken on the coals, and a cruſe of water at his head; and he did eat and drink, and laid him down again.</hi> And when he had eaten again, he went in the ſtrength of that meat forty days and forty nights unto <hi>Horeb</hi> the mount of God. Such a bleſſing did God give to it, that made it ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to ſuſtain him for ſo long a time. When the Hoſts of the Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Judah</hi> were diſtreſſed for want of water, they ſought to God by the Prophet <hi>Eliſha,</hi> and God gave them plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of water in their great neceſſity. 2 Kings 3.16—. <hi>And he ſaid, Thus ſaith the Lord, make this valley full of ditches. For thus ſaith the Lord, ye ſhall not ſee wind, neither ſhall ye ſee rain, yet that valley ſhall be filled with water, that ye may drink, both ye, and your cattle, and your beaſts.</hi> And ver. 20. <hi>And it came to paſs in the morning, when the meat-offring was offered, that behold, there came water by the way of Edom, and the country was filled with water.</hi> And we may ſee in the Goſpels that our bleſſed Saviour did often feed many thouſands with a few loaves and a little quantity of fiſh, when he ſaw it needful to work ſuch a miracle for them. By theſe and ſuch Inſtances we ſee how God hath in an extraordinary manner relieved his People and Servants in their great neceſſities, and ſupplyed them with food and ſuch things as they ſtood in great need of.</p>
            <p n="2">2, We may ſee alſo that Almighty God hath often delivered his People and Servants in an extraordinary and miraculous man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner from great and eminent Dangers, and from ſuch Judgments and Calamities as have befallen others. God preſerved <hi>Noah</hi> from that prodigious Flood that ſwept away the Inhabitants of the old World in his time, and drowned all Mankind beſide him and his Family. <hi>Gen.</hi> 7.1—. He protected <hi>Abraham</hi> in all his travels, and delivered him from all his fears. He preſerved him from being hurt by the <hi>Egytians, Gen.</hi> 12: And from the hands of the four Kings that took <hi>Lot</hi> captive, againſt whom he war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, <hi>Gen.</hi> 14: And out of all other ſtraits that he came into, did he deliver him. He preſerved <hi>Lot</hi> from that dreadful judgment of fire, that deſtroyed the Cities of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah</hi> &amp;c.
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:47917:20"/> 
               <hi>Gen.</hi> 19. He kept <hi>Jacob</hi> from being hurt by his Brother <hi>Eſau,</hi> when he came out with an Hoſt of 400 men againſt him, and turned his heart ſo that he did him no harm, but embraced him in love; <hi>Gen.</hi> 33.4. He protected <hi>Moſes</hi> from being hurt by <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh</hi> King of <hi>Egypt,</hi> when he came to deliver the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> out of his hand; and armed him with ſuch power of doing wonders, that he made him like a God to <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> as he ſaith, <hi>Exod.</hi> 7.1. And he preſerved him all along afterwards in all thoſe dangers that he underwent; and from the hands of thoſe Kings with whom he warred, over whom he gave him victory: And pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved his People <hi>Iſrael</hi> from all the dangers that they met with. He protected <hi>Joſhua</hi> and his People afterwards from all the Kings of <hi>Canaan,</hi> and gave him victory over them and their Armies, as we may ſee in the book of <hi>Joſhua.</hi> The Lord pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved <hi>David</hi> from all the attempts of King <hi>Saul</hi> to take away his life, and at the laſt ſet him upon the Throne of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> And hereby we may ſee how vain a thing it is to ſeek to take away his life, whom the God of Heaven will preſerve; and how thoſe that ſet upon ſuch enterprizes, like <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> do moſt miſerably fret and gall themſelves; and that diſappointment and grief are the fruits of ſuch ſinful attempts. In a miraculous manner did the Lord deliver the Prophet <hi>Elijah</hi> from the two Captains and their men, that were ſent from the King of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to take him; and ſent down fire from Heaven to conſume them; 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 1.9—: And from <hi>Jezebel,</hi> and all dangers elſe did God deliver him. The Lord delivered the Prophet <hi>Eliſha</hi> from the Bands of the <hi>Syrians,</hi> and garded him with Horſes and Chariots of fire; 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 6.15—: And from the King of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when he ſent to take away his head; and from all dangers elſe did God deliver him. The Lord in a remarkable manner delivered <hi>Samaria</hi> and the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> from the Hoſt of <hi>Syria</hi> (2 <hi>Kings</hi> 7.6—) and frighted the whole Hoſt away, and made them to overrun their Tents and Horſes through fear. The Lord preſerved and delivered King <hi>Hezekiah</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> in a miraculous manner from <hi>Sennacherib</hi> the King of <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> and ſent his Angel to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy his whole Army; 2 Kings 19.35. <hi>And it came to paſs that night, that the Angel of the Lord went out, and ſmote in the Camp
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:47917:21"/> of the Aſſyrians an hundred and fourſcore and five thouſand, and when they aroſe early in the morning, behold they were all dead corpſes.</hi> In a wonderful manner were the three Children preſerved and kept from harm, even in the midſt of the fiery Furnace by the Omnipotent power of God: Dan. 3.26—: <hi>Then Shadrach Meſhach and Abednego came forth of the midſt of the fire. And the Princes, Governors and Captains, and the King's Counſellors, being gathered together, ſaw theſe men upon whoſe bodies the fire had no power, nor was an hair of their head ſinged, neither were their coats changed, nor the ſmell of fire had paſſed on them.</hi> In this extreme danger, and hopeleſs condition to all humane appearance, were they thus miraculouſly delivered, and had not the leaſt degree of harm. The Prophet <hi>Daniel</hi> was protected and defended by an Angel in the Lyon's den from being torn in pieces, or hurt by them; Dan. 6.21—; <hi>Then ſaid Daniel unto the King, O King, live for ever. My God hath ſent his Angel, and hath ſhut the lyons mouthes, that they have not hurt me; for as much as before him innocency was found in me: and alſo before thee, O King, have I done no hurt.</hi> The Lord by an Angel delivered St. <hi>Peter</hi> out of priſon, and out of the hands of <hi>Herod,</hi> who was minded to put him to death: Acts 12.7—: <hi>And behold the Angel of the Lord came upon him</hi> (ſaith St. Luke) <hi>and a light ſhined in the priſon, and he ſmote Peter on the ſide, and raiſed him up, ſaying, Ariſe up quickly. And his chains fell off from his hands. And the Angel ſaid unto him, gird thy ſelf, and bind on thy ſandals. And ſo he did. And he ſaith unto him, caſt thy garments about thee, and follow me. And he went out, and followed him</hi>—. By theſe and ſuch like examples we may ſee, That God hath delivered and protected his People and Servants from very great and eminent dangers in a wonderful and miraculous manner, when they have had no power and might to help and defend themſelves. And from hence we may be the more encouraged to put our truſt and confidence in him, and hope that he will have pity and mercy upon us, and ſend us help and relief in all our ſtraits and needs and helpleſs conditions, if we have recourſe to him, and depend upon him for help and protection and relief at all times, as we ought. We have all the aſſurance that well can be that
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:47917:21"/> God will no ways fail us in the day of trouble; And we have as great encouragement as we can well deſire, to truſt in the Lord <hi>Jehovah</hi> at all times of the greateſt Dangers: And if we can but believe his ſacred and ſure Word, and rely upon his faithful Promiſes, we need not much to fear in the darkeſt and blackeſt Times that can come upon us, ſuch as this is like to be. If we are not wanting to our ſelves, but will repent and ſeek to God, and truſt in him alone, he will never be wanting to us, but will be ſure to be with us at all times as need ſhall require; And even at the Stake, if we ſhould be brought thither, will he be with us to ſupport us, as he was with St. <hi>Stephen, Acts</hi> 7.55. And even now will the Lord God Almighty aſſume and take to himſelf his great Power, and will Reign, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.17: that is, will Reign in a magnificent and glorious manner, and make mortal men to know in the end, that it is He which ruleth in the Kingdoms of men, and diſpoſeth of them as he ſees good. Now will he exert and put forth his Almighty Arm for the protection and defence of his Church and Servants in their forlorn and helpleſs condition. And when we have ſeen this, we are to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate that Heavenly Aſſembly of Elders, and to ſing Alleluja's to him, and to return thanks to the Lord God Omnipotent, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he hath ſo viſibly ſet up his Standard here among us, and hath Reigned in ſuch a glorious and renowed manner for the preſervation of his Church and Servants. Now in the end of this dark Time that is coming upon us, will the Lord God Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent ſhake the Earth and the great City too (<hi>Rev.</hi> 11.13.) and affright the Inhabitants thereof, and make them to give glory to the God of Heaven. And then are the Enemies of the Proteſtant Church to expect that the ſecond dreadful Wo will be executed upon them. <hi>And in the earth-quake</hi> (ſaith St. John) <hi>were ſlain of men ſeven thouſand.</hi> Which number ſeems to be put not ſtrictly for juſt ſeven thouſand, but for an exceeding great number of men that ſhall be then ſlain. [See the Letter of a Proteſtant Clergy-man—.] And therefore we had need to take great care that we do not fall to Popery, and ſo periſh in this Deſtruction. We ought to take great care that we fall not from God to any ſinful practices; for hereby we ſhall do our ſelves more harm than all our Enemies can do to us. By <hi>Rev.</hi> 11, we
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:47917:22"/> may ſee that Popery ſhall prevail for three years and an half, and that then after this time is exſpired the Proteſtant Church ſhall be as glorious as ever it was before. And from this XI Chapter we have aſſurance of God's extraordinary help and protection even at this very time, that he will in a wonderful man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner defend his Church and Servants, and fight for them againſt their Enemies; And after this ſhort time of Tryal, will exalt them again. And this will be an exceeding great Support and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to us in our mournful and forlorn condition, to know this before-hand, and to be aſſured of it by Divine Revelation. We may even look upon the Divine Conſolation that God gave to his People the <hi>Jews</hi> by the Prophet, as ſpoken to us. Iſ. 26.20. <hi>Come, my People, enter thou into thy chambers, and ſhut thy doors about thee; hide thy ſelf as it were for a little moment, untill the Indignation be over-paſt.</hi> With Faith and Patience we may well wait upon God for ſuch a little time, when he, for wiſe and righteous ends does permit ſuch a Tragical Scene of affairs to be brought upon the Stage of the world. And now to conclude,</p>
            <p>Seeing our God is ſuch a Rock of Salvation againſt all that can befall us; ſeeing he knows and regards our conditions and all our Dangers and Needs and Wants, and is both able and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to help and ſuccour us upon all accounts; ſeeing he hath given ſo great Aſſurance that he will never fail us and be wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to us, if we ſerve him and truſt in him; Let us then not be Infidels and Faithleſs in ſo clear a Light, but let us be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed upon to make him, and him alone, our Rock and Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and betake our ſelves to him at all times of Danger and Diſtreſs for help and relief. Though we have ſinned and been great Tranſgreſſors, and ſo given him too great a cauſe to caſt off his protection and care of us; yet if we repent and return to him, he is prone to mercy, and therefore we may chearfully hope that he will yet be our Almighty God and Protector. Let us all then bid adieu to all our ſinful and evil ways, and ſet our ſelves ſeriouſly and earneſtly to ſeek the Lord of Hoſts, and then we ſhall be ſure to find him, and to find him a Mighty God for us in the needful time of trouble and diſtreſs. Let us addreſs our ſelves to him in earneſt prayer and faſting, that he would be graciouſly pleaſed to paſs by our Tranſgreſſions, and to pity
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:47917:22"/> and help us in all the perilous conditions and miſeries that befal us. Let us call upon him with the man in the Goſpel (<hi>Mar.</hi> 9.24) to ſuccour and help our unbelief, to encreaſe and ſtrengthen our Faith in him, and to confirm our hopes and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in his great Mercy and Goodneſs, that we may at all times chearfully depend and rely upon him, and never doubt and deſpair of his Almighty Help and Protection. I conclude all with that Collect of our Church, ordered to be uſed upon the fourth Sunday after <hi>Epiphany.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>O God, who knoweſt us to be ſet in the midſt of ſo many and great dangers, that by reaſon of the frailty of our nature we cannot always ſtand upright; Grant to us ſuch ſtrength and protection as may ſupport us in all dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and carry us through all temptations, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi> Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>IN the Watchman's Voice. P. 19. L. 3. r. forbearance. l. 21. r. Romiſh. p. 20. l. 25. r. ſinners. p. 26. l. 4. r. Jailer. l. 15. r. at another. p. 43. l. 22. r. we are not.</p>
            <p>In the Letter. p. 1. l. 1. r. Laity. p. 14. l. 6. r. Angels. p. 15. l. 29. r. Papiſts. p. 17. l. 5. r. the Saints. p. 22. l. 33. r. that. p, 23. l. 6. r. Emperors. p. 29. l. 18. r. and an half. p. 47. l. 6. r. marginal. p. 57. l. 6. r. Tranquility. p. 58. l. 22. r. of time. p. 59. l. 5. r. Rome. p. 62. l. 22. r. Providence.</p>
            <p>In the contrariety of Popery, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> p. 5. l. 23. r. yea Lord p. 16. l. 2. r. directions. l. 26. r. Apoſtle. p. 24. l. 2. r. Not. p. 27. l. 11. r. effected. p. 46. l. 16. r. (ſaith he) p. 47. l. 5. r. not to marry. p. 53. l. 8. r. ſaith he.</p>
            <p>In the Church's Requeſt. p. 5. l. 10. r. Tranquility. p. 31. l. 2. r. we were. l. 33. r. truly. l. 37. r. fulfilled. p. 35. l. 5. r. or wiſe. l. 20. r. you. p. 36. l. 11. r. confounded.</p>
            <p>In the Exhortation to truſt in God. p. 9. l. 28. r. thou. p. 11. l. 17. r. poſſeſs. p. 15. l. 38. r. his. p. 20. l. 38. r. handy-work. p. 22. l. 29. r. ſubtile.</p>
            <p>P ſtands for page. L for line. R for read.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
